so thank you very much for the
opportunity to to speak to y'all as I
mentioned like I'm not feeling a hundred
percents from my voice might be giving
in but it's it's okay well well give it
give it a try and I really enjoyed
seeing all the questions I'll try
briefly whether I can share the screen
can people see me on a bigger screen or
oh okay then then I'll see if I can
share one slide with you just because it
helps to answer the the first question
let me just see if this works this one
can you see the slide the graphic now
yeah okay the it's quite a dense graphic
but it's it's a useful way of describing
and contextualizing a little bit the
first question which was how do you
distinguish between regenerative design
and sustainable design and you could
also call it regenerative development
and sustainable development so this
graphic um is an evolution of a graphic
that I first saw bill read use in 2006
in an article called shifting our mental
models which if you put that into a
search engine you should find the
original article and what I really liked
about it is that it puts on a spectrum
the journey that that we now have to
make rapidly and and because it puts it
on the spectrum and the energy in it
depicts it as a journey it doesn't
negate or dismiss any stage of the
journey it just says there is road ahead
and there is a as a larger goal and in
many ways you could summarize this
journey from that the conventional
businesses usual practice that that most
businesses and and most governments are
engaged in is basically to legislate to
a certain extent what kind of
environmental and social
behavior is allowed and and what our
transgressions and create legal
frameworks that keep people somewhat
within certain boundaries but of course
we we know that those boundaries are
still by and large degenerative
and-and-and that there are structural
problems with the system to a point that
we continued to degrade our communities
and our environment so the next step
then from a perspective of a company
would be to do a little bit more than
just stay within the legal limits use a
little bit more renewable energy maybe
plant some bio diverse gardens around
the company's headquarters and all those
kind of things and then over communicate
it in in the marketing side of the
company and that's often called green
washing but but in many ways those
little steps are steps and therefore
shouldn't be completely dismissed and
then in this framework the word
sustainable is reserved for those things
that don't add any more damage
but in in many ways this neutral no
impact not being part of the problem but
also in a way not being part of the
solution is not enough anymore because
depending on where we start I like to
actually start with with agriculture in
developing and the wrong type of
agriculture being practiced some 8,000
years ago and through that a study is
starting to denude the forest the the
planet by cutting down forests which
we've cut on about half of the world's
forests in the last eight thousand years
um that kind of damage that we've done
and in particular since the Industrial
Revolution over the last 250 years we
have done so much damage to the
environment that simply doing no harm is
not enough and it's really the same also
for social damage because particularly
with since colonialization and then the
second wave of sort of neo-colonial is a
ssin in the form of neoliberal economic
expansion and globalization and
we we have destroyed communities all
around the globe or eroded social fabric
and so we really need to do much more
than than just have low negative impact
and then the next step on this spectrum
is called restorative and while it
already is trying to undo some of the
damage underneath it says humans doing
things to nature so it's still done in a
mindset that says okay let's bring the
Indian Army in and beat the world record
in how many trees we can plant in a day
which is wonderful to see that people
can plant a million trees or more in a
single day if everybody works together
but if you don't care for the trees
afterwards then a little bit of
gardening and forestry knowledge will
tell you that maybe one two maximum ten
percent of those trees would survive if
you don't resource and engage the people
to take care of those million trees
they're planted so so these the
restorative mindset does good things but
by still being in the mindset that that
is has the human arrogance that we
somehow are outside of nature and that
we somehow have the right to to control
manipulate and and and change the more
than human nature patterns in the world
is still part of the problem and so the
real important step towards working
regenerative Lee is to understand that
as one of my compatriots good was more
famous as as a literary man but he was
also a scientist said over 200 years ago
who doesn't see nature everywhere sees
her nowhere in the right light who
doesn't see nature everywhere sees her
nowhere in the right light and for me
that's really an interesting invitation
to start to think even about our
technologies as part of the biophysical
unity that is life as a planetary
process and the biosphere transforming
over millennia and an even longer time
spans
and it means that even our technologies
even nuclear power plants are part of
those natural cycles but in many ways
they are maladaptive and they will not
continue to give our species of future
sorry there's a problem in back I don't
know if you can hear the the beeping and
it's just stopped okay so in a nutshell
sustainable design is still very
important sustainability is still very
important I think sustainability is a
bridge that we haven't passed yet and
the danger in in what's happening right
now with so many people getting excited
about the regenerative impulse and the
the the movement of regeneration all
around the world is that many people who
have the habit consultants who always
look for the the newest trend will will
jump onto this regenerative term and
added to whatever they're doing already
instead of sustainability and and start
to discourse so if our sustainability is
so old and not fashionable anymore
everybody wants to be reset regenerative
now but that's really not what this is
about
it's it's really to honor that we still
need to do a lot of work to become
sustainable but to set the goal much
further out and say actually as life we
have the capacity to regenerate our
communities regenerate local and by
regional economies and regenerate the
ecosystems in which we live as part of
those ecosystems so we start to design
as nature rather than design or do
things to nature and briefly I just want
to point out like so I put the SDGs the
the UN discourse on development or
sustainable development right in the
center here but I want to point out that
I've slightly changed the SDG number-8
icon um might if you look carefully you
might see that there's a little spanner
em on that icon now and I do that on
purpose to highlight that in the current
framing of the sustainable development
goals within the goals is the sabotaging
element that will stop us from
implementing all 17 goals and that is
the way that we're currently framing SDG
number eight it's still called decent
work and continued economic growth and
the problem that has driven
unsustainable or degenerative
development is that structurally we
designed a economic system that needs
continued economic growth in order to
survive to continue and this growth
imperative and the fundamental structure
of the economic and monetary system that
is a zero sum game which needs losers
for other people's to be able to win is
a system that ultimately drives us to
exploit the planet and exploit each
other and so there is a structurally
this structural dysfunctionality in our
current economic and monetary system
that unless we address that we will not
be able to implement the seventeen SDGs
and cross that bridge towards
regeneration
that's at least my firm conviction so
and then just briefly some other changes
that we need to make on the path towards
working more regenerative leave you can
see under on the left hand side it says
designing technical systems we're
obsessed with mechanistic and
technological metaphors we even explain
consciousness and the brain using
computers as an example and anybody
who's ever seen a little baby grow up
and will see that that biology is so
much more clever than we are and that
there are so many more complex processes
in in life unfolding that even our
highest technology is actually really
quite simple and crude compared to what
life is doing constantly
and and so those technological and and
mechanistic metaphors keep us in a sort
of mindset that doesn't really help help
us in creating truly regenerative
solutions
similarly the the way that our
intellectual landscape is fragmented
into the different disciplines that are
taught at universities and the different
specialties that people become experts
in and and then make their their
financial income from then all of that
has created a wealth of knowledge and
it's not that it's not important and
it's not that we should completely
dismiss all this but we need to put it
in in its place and we need to
understand that and with every
perspective comes a blind-spot and and
therefore we need to value multiple
perspectives and and pay attention to
the blind spots of each one of them and
talk to each other to create more
integrative solutions and it also be in
in a similar vein this since the
Scientific Revolution this focus on on
mechanism and technology and science has
brought in a way of seeing that if you
can't quantify it it's not there I mean
Galileo said this many many a couple of
centuries ago they did there two types
of qualities the qualities you can
measure and the qualities you can't
measure and he basically said science
has to work with only the measurable
which is basically what we've done and
what which we now call quantifiable
indicators and so even as you like I see
this when when I did at work when my
book came out in in Brazil and a lot of
people in Brazil were asking so what are
the indicators of success for
regenerative companies give me the the
indicators I can work with as a
consultant with companies and they're
always pushing towards creating easily
quantifiable indicators and they might
give us an indication and I'm not saying
we shouldn't find some but my point is
that really we need to pay much more
attention about qualities to qualities
because when you engage in regenerative
practice in communities
it is the qualitative changes of
relationships between people between
people and their environment between
people in their ecosystem and that
really matter and yes to some extent we
can find proxies that are quantifiable
that express these qualitative changes
but there's always something important
that is lost so really working
regenerative lis is understanding
embracing our uncertainty embracing our
inability to predict and control the
complexity of natural systems that we
are part of and to shift from this this
control and manipulation mindset to a
mindset of appropriate participation in
these patterns and and it's also a shift
from this fragmented thinking of of the
the expert which can be valued and
listened to to a more integrative
thinking that also values the
capabilities of generalists and people
who synthesized as well wealth of
knowledge we created and and really find
solutions that serve all of humanity and
serve all of life because ultimately one
of these fragmented habits with that
that made us see the world we see it now
is paying attention to life as a a
collection of individuals and the
collection of species somehow fighting
against each other but but if you shift
perspective and look at the planet as a
whole then very quickly you can
understand that life is actually a
planetary process and that in the
evolution of life cooperation and
collaboration has been much more
influential in each major step of
evolution than competition and
competition is just the fine tuning on
the surface the ripples on the oceans
the waves that attract our attention but
cooperation and symbiosis and working
together to create conditions conducive
to life is the vast ocean to all the
depth of the Marianas Trench of life as
a planetary symbiotic process so that's
just too
I'll stop sharing now just to give you
an overall framework to answer to some
extent the first question and took took
a while but I think it's worth it and I
I've sent this PDF to your teacher and
so you can hopefully get a PDF of it and
use it